<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An apology vindicating the Cavaleers from a partiall, or rather a passionate aspersion too rigorously put upon them for making churches prisons and stables. Wherein is discussed, disputed, (although not the lawfulnesse) yet (at this time) the unavoydable necessity of it.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75511</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3560</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E102_18</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11539</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859060</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859060</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111121</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75511)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111121)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 18:E102[18])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An apology vindicating the Cavaleers from a partiall, or rather a passionate aspersion too rigorously put upon them for making churches prisons and stables. Wherein is discussed, disputed, (although not the lawfulnesse) yet (at this time) the unavoydable necessity of it.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare 1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Offenses against religion --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111121:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN APOLOGY, Vindicating the CAVALEERS from a partiall, or rather a paſſionate aſperſion too rigorouſly put upon them for making Churches Priſons and Stables. <hi>Wherein is diſcuſſed, diſputed,</hi> (<hi>although</hi> not the lawfulneſſe) yet (at this time) the unavoydable neceſſity of it.</p>
            <p>London Printed in the yeare, 1643.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:111121:2"/>
            <head>AN APOLOGY, Vindicating the Cavaleers, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Any of this Kingdome, have ſeemed of late to be much troubled, (I cannot ſay in conſcience, untill it better appeare by their converſations; that they make a conſcience of any thing, therefore, let it be trouble in their thoughts,) and trouble others with their ſilly diſcourſes, about the throwing downe of Organs, ſilencing of Cathedrall Roarers, and Squeakers, bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering of Images, defacing the Popiſh paint, &amp; gaudery of Churches, and aſſaulting immodeſtly forſooth, and irregiouſly, not onely that ſacred ſmock of the whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> the Surplice, but alſo the formaliſts grand Charter for Heaven, the Common prayer Book: all this while theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout men have not beene at all perplexed, or moved at that piacular inſolence, and more then heatheniſh impiety of the Cavaleers at <hi>Oxford, Kingſtone</hi> upon <hi>Thames,</hi> &amp; <hi>Cirenceſter,</hi> have not onely made priſons, but by the inhumane reſtraint of their Priſoners, Jakes, &amp; in <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> and <hi>Cornwall</hi> ſtables of Gods houſes; ſo reverentiall and devoutly tender of the honour of Gods houſes, have theſe Biſhops white boyes been, who yet in the account of ſome half witted Guls, are the onely Patrons both of Church men, and Churches, &amp; the truely zealous advancers of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion. The ſerious conſideration of which premiſes, cals to my remembrance, that no leſſe true then famous axiome of Divines, <hi>quicquid propter Deum fit aequaliter fit</hi> (1) what is done to Gods glory, is alwaies
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:111121:2"/>done upon the ſame occaſions, for he that honoureth God upon true Grounds will honour him impartially, and at all opportunities alike; by the help of which ſubſtantiall ground I ſhall at once confute both the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the diſſembling Cavalier, and alſo the opinions and diſcourſes of thoſe formall Proteſtants, who upon all occaſions decry the Browniſt and his practice, and yet have not an ill word for theſe curſed Cavaliers, who farre tranſcend the Browniſt in that very particular, whereof the Browniſt in their miſguided partiall judgement ſtand guilty.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, if the Cavalier in good earneſt diſlike the rudeneſſe of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratiſt, in laying violent hands upon theſe ſacred Utenſills, appointed by our holy mother-Church, for the ſetting forth of Gods worſhip with more luſter, and a ſtronger Influence upon the dull affections of the vulgar, why doth the ſame Rake-hell ſo farre forget his own diſcourſe, as to unhallow not onely the ſacred implements, but the very Churches themſelves, if his eye were all on Gods glory, in his accuſations of the Separatiſt? he might ſee as juſt cauſe to condemne himſelf, who doth the ſame thing in a more notorious manner, if any love to God ſet his tongue on work againſt the Separatiſt, it would teach his hand to abſtain from that which he ſo deeply cenſures in the other.</p>
            <p>Secondly, tell me, thou lukewarm, or rather key-cold Proteſtant, who art alwayes ſnarling at theſe poore deſpiſed Chriſtians, whoſe practiſe thinkeſt thou is more ſcandalous, the Browniſt's, who out of conſcience la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to purge our Churches of theſe Babiloniſh Reliques, or the Cavalier (who at leaſt without, if not againſt Conſcience) transformes the very Churches themſelves into Priſons, Stables, Jakes? didſt thou adore theſe ſtinking Cavaliers onely (as thou ſaiſt) for their zeal and Religion to Gods houſes, then couldeſt thou not hold alſo from defilng them for their unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ampled polluting of them: either then ſpare the laſh of thy venomous tongue towards the one, or elſe ſpit thy venome alſo at the other.</p>
            <p>Our Saviour thou knoweſt (if I may without offence mention that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred name, when I talk of theſe varlet) tells us that the temple is greater, and holier then either the Altar, or gold upon the Altar, and accounts of the Scribes, and Phariſees, as of blind buzzards, who thought otherwiſe <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.17. If it be ſo then I hope the blind formaliſt by the ſame force of reaſon will be convinced, that the churches themſelves deſerve more reverence from us, then Organes or other Popiſh trumpery; if therefore thou haſt any heart (thou beſotted ignorant formaliſt) to put in practiſe the former golden rule above mentioned, fail not to remember that when
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111121:3"/>thou diſgorgeſt thy rancor againſt Separatiſts for diſhonouring Gods houſe, thou oughteſt at the ſame time to beſpatter the Cavalier, who much more diſhonours it; if thou forget this thy duty inforc'd upon the ſame ground, then take it not amiſſe, if thou be herafter accounted by every wiſe man that heats thee a ſhameleſſe Cenſor; and that thou rather diſcouereſt thy malignant humour then any judgement, when thou ſeverely reprehendeſt the one, and ſpareſt the other, who more juſtly deſerves thy bittereſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions.</p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding all that hath been ſaid, or (it may be) can be ſaid, are there not ſome ſo impudent as to palliate and varniſh ouer this curſed fact, who yet keep on barking at the poore ſeparatiſt? nay are not ſome grave Doctors of that Univerſity, where this fact was committed who have had the fore-heads not onely in their private diſcourſes, but (I would I could not ſay it) in the pulpet, as it were in deſpight of all that which hath hitherto been preached &amp; written, by that practiſe to the contrary, to legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate that baſe action and proclaime it not onely lawfull and ſeemely, but laudable? and now here I beſeech you upon what learned grounds theſe grave beaſts have ſo determin'd it? becauſe forſooth the Cavaliers were neceſſitated to what they did, wanting other convenient receptacles for their priſoners. Eye upon that foule mouth that ſaid it, fouler I wis then thoſe profane Churches after a months defilement: for were there in all <hi>Oxford</hi> no unſanctified Colledges, which might with more convenience and leſſe ſcandall have been converted into Priſons and Jakes then God houſes? to my apprehenſion, rather then you ſhould have ſo thwarted your Epiſcopal doctrine, by ſuch an unheard of preſident at ſuch a time, when your zeale for Churches and their ornaments ſhould have been moſt conſpicuous, had it not been much better, and more advantageous to your cauſe that your ſelves had wanted for a time the convenience of houſes, then that Gods houſes ſhould bee ſo fouly diſhonoured. <hi>Vobis ipſis ſpectantibus &amp; plauden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentibus,</hi> whilſt your ſelves were lookers on, nay applauders and collourers of ſo ſhamefull an action? eſpecially ſince you cannot, but have freſh in your memory, that at the reedifying of St. <hi>Pauls Church</hi> at London, good St. Gregories was demoliſhed by the Command of your then great <hi>Metropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litane,</hi> that ſo St. Pauls might have the more elbow-room, for no man hath yet heard of any other cauſe, whence I thus reaſon; If God himſelfe may be caſhiered of a Church meerely out of a ſilly complement to St. Paul, your ſelves might with patience have layen in the ſtreets (a decent lodging for ſuch Atheiſts) for the preſeruing Gods houſe from ſuch unexpiable diſhonour.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:111121:3"/>
            <p>Yea but another Reverend beaſt ſaid that this diſuſe (how finely the man could phraſe it) of theſe Churches, was onely for ſome ſhort time; he that ſaid ſo, might as well excuſe a ſonne that raviſheth his Mother, by ſaying he did it onely for a time; can the beggarly circumſtance of ime excuſe that tedious practiſe which ſhould not ſo much as lodge in your thoughts, the leaſt minute of time? Moreover the people of <hi>Oxford</hi> know for how long time this Sacrieledge was continued, and how ready the ſame men are (ſhould God permit them any more to conquer, which the baſe uſe of their paſt victories will, I doubt not, avert) to doe the like or a more impious and ſcandalous act at any time</p>
            <p>But it hath been gravely anſwered: that the Priſoners, good men had their option, at leaſt deſerved no other place of their reſtraint then Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. Had theſe Caytifs knowne ſo much, they had queſtionleſſe found priſons ſome where elſe; leaſt in any thing theſe poore Saints ſhould by their meanes have had their deſires; againe theſe poore men though they moſt of all love Gods houſes, yet know, that to love them for ſuch uſes, had been to have loved the abuſes of them which were not to love them.</p>
            <p>Another incarnate Divell ſaid aloud, that ſuch Puritans deſerved in that houſe to be purniſht, where by their preciſenes they had ſo often offended; which is all one as if he had ſaid, they deſerve there to be puniſhed, where God had been by them ſo devoutly ſerv'd. What reward waites for thee thou Heliſh tongue? <hi>ſimilis labra luctueas,</hi> a blaſphemy well beſeeming a Court divine; nevertheleſſe the truth is, what ever pretences they have ſought out for the palliating this unparalel'd piece of Atheiſme, for ſo it would have been accounted three yeares ſince, even by the whole rabble of theſe Cathedrall Sycophants, the true cauſe I ſay of this vile fact was none other then the baſe eſteeme (however they have ſeem'd to carry it) that party hath of Churches of which as formerly they ſpeak with reverence, and entered them with great ſhew of devotion, and at other mens charges adorn'd, &amp; ſet them forth with all manner encomioms of holynes, ſo now the tide of things being ſomewhat turn'd, and Policy coming in the room of ſhewfull Pageantlike devotions, as a more helpfull aſſiſtant to the preſent exigences: now I ſay the ſame men whoſe thoughts were wholly poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſ'd with Popiſh projects of attiring Churches; thereby to approve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> man Idoll, are as well content that the ſame Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ſhould be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> vileſt offices: Nay moſt confident I am, and ſo I beleeve are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> who have with diſcretion lookt into their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeumbled outward <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> that ſo their cauſe may be advanced by it,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111121:4"/>the beſt of them care not, if all the Churches in England were converted into ſynagogues for Jewes, or Moſques for Mahomet, nay their height of joy it would be, if all our Churches were turned (as of late ſome of them you know have beene) into Priſons, ſo Puritans and Roundheads fill'd them: and if all manner of ſervice of God were for ever laid aſide upon condition the title of their Lordly revennues were chang'd from frank Almoygne to fee ſimple, whereby they might durably entayle their pride and luxury upon their licentious brats and poſterity.</p>
            <p>Had not ſome ſuch chriſtian thoughts and deſires as theſe, lodged in the breaſts of our Court-Clergy-Paraſites at <hi>Oxford,</hi> it is impoſſible but that upon view or notice of that Publique Profanation of their Churches, either ſome Arch-biſhop, or Biſhop or Doctor, eſpecially that Ceremonious Maſter of Baliol Colledge Do. Laur. who wore the conſecrated ſlippers, and ſpent moſt of his ſtock of learning upon that empty diſcourſe of his, touching the holineſſe of churches, ſhould not have made way to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, and after this or the like manner have eaſ'd his couſcience, and expreſt himſelf to his ſacred perſon.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="sermon">
                  <body>
                     <p>Moſt gracious Soveraigne, defender of the truly anncient Catholique faith, and the great protector both of Churches and Churchmen.</p>
                     <p>I humbly crave your Mateſties gracious pardon that I your Maieſties moſt unworthy ſervant, yet truly loyall ſubiect dare adventure to open my mouth before your ſacred Mateſtie, having not firſt received your Maieſties commands for the unlooſing my infant tongue.</p>
                     <p>Your all knowing Maieſtie cannot but exactly know and it hath been a ſubiect frequently ſtood upon and gravely preſſed in your Maieſties audience, by your Maieſties moſt faithfull ſubiects and ſervants the Arch-biſhops, Biſhops and other of your learned Clergy, whoſe happineſſe it hath been to performe their duties before your Maieſtie in the houſe of God. That the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall Churches or Temples are places ſet apart &amp; conſecrated to Gods pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar ſervice. That God himſelfe whom the Heaven of Heavens cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, delights to dwell in theſe houſes made with hands, vouchſafes a ſpeciall preſence unto them, and conferrs at the inſtance and devout importunity of his pious ſervants are all though ineffable holineſſe upon them, and therefore in all ages of the Church, more eſpecially in the purest times when the ſeemly worſhip of God moſt flouriſht, a ſingular care hath been alwayes taken to preſerve theſe ſacred fabricks from common uſes, eſpecially from Proſanation; in imitation whereof (for your divine Maieſtie cannot fall ſhort in any point of the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Chriſtian Princes) there is, at leaſt hath been of late yeares under your
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111121:4"/>Maieſties moſt religious Raigne, the beauty of holineſſe ſo farre forth to be found in your Mateſties Churches, that in deſpight of theſe ignorant peeviſh male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents who care not or rather deſire that Gods houſes ſhould be as undecently or ſluttiſhly kept as their ſhops or Barnes? Churches have been to admiration adorned, Altars erected, Copes, Tapers, Crucifixes and other comely and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ornaments brought in uſe againe, and by your Maieſties countenance, and the vigilancie of the Reverend Fathers of your Church, the antient and ſoule-raviſhing worſhip of God ſo ſetled, not onely in your Churches but alſo in the affections of your ſubiects, that a proportionable reward thereof in this life, the choyſeſt bleſſing of Heaven ſurrounded your royall throne, the maligners of your Maieſties Diadem and the ſacred Miter, find few, at leaſt, no conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable advocates. Indeed it cannot be diſſembl'd that of very late dayes by the mighty working of Setan, theſe coutemptibe muſhromes (but now touched at) diſcovering a diſcontented party though from different grounds from them) amongſt the Nobles and Commons in the late Parliament of your Maiesties own moſt Gracious calling, who envying the happineſſe of your Maiesties meniall ſervants, and ſome ſelect Miniſters of ſtate, whom the beames of your Maiesties Grace had moſt inſtly made glorious, or (which is neareſt of all the truth, lowring at your Maieſties royall ſcepter, &amp; Prerogative, a tribe of Politicks deſtitute of all deſerts, or elſe your omniſcious Maiesty had certainly taken notice of them) yet highly conceited of an indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coverable, worth and eminency in themſelves, and a ſuitableneſſe to high employments, which God knowes they eminently want; unto this ſeed of evill doers permitted by the Divine Providence in your Kingdome, onely to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe the vertues of your accompliſhed Councell, have this onely reſerve of turbulent Cartwrights <hi>Geneva</hi> novelty applied themſelves, and in requitall of their craſty ſimpathizing with their Rebellions ends, have been admitted into their confederacy, who ſo gracious with them, as theſe Church-racking, tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuous ſpirits, theſe every where unprotected and baffled Sectaries, who again the better to gratifie their new maſters, and to approve themſelves, and (which is their meat and drink) to doe miſchiefs, upon apprehenſions of their new patrons deſigne fell ſpeedily, and furiouſly (as their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is) to work, blew the coules moſt zealouſly to their Rebellious enterpriſe, diſparaged the Crown: blemiſhed that intaminate Peereleſſe Conſort, in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing inferiour to that greateſt ſaint of her name in heaven, but immortality, threw dirt in abundance upon the ſacred Miter. buzzed impure notions of licenſe, and independency into the credulous vulgar, in a word ſo plaid their parts in ſcurrilous libells, Sermons, diſcourſes, that in ſhort time, they which
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:111121:5"/>ſet them a work had nothing almoſt left for themſelves to doe, but onely to admire the dexteritie, and ſucceſſefullneſſe of theſe formerly contemned inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Whereupon their new maſters abundantly ſenſible of their ſufficiency began to unfold themſelves more freely unto them, nay threw open a wide gap to their familiarity ſolaſ't each other in their low ungrac'd condition as Caius Marius and Carthage did of old in the Hiſtorian prayd together for the confuſion of the Churches and Kingdomes glory.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>*</hi> Velleius Paterculus.</note> Prerogative and Prelacy; indeed by Gods connivance in Proceſſe of time, ſo it came to paſſe, that this mongrel monſtrous beaſt begotten betweene a ſectary and an envious Peere, ſo thrived and gathered ſtrength whether thorough the novelty of the proiect (for the Vulgar are uſualy raviſhed with new fangles) or the activity and zeale of theſe curſed incendiaries, who left no ſtone unroll'd to bring about the deſigne; your Maieſties Cathedrall ſubiects were put into a bodily feare, that their fatall period and deſolation was drawing neere, and that Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy (which I tremble to relate) was either to be devorſed from Prerogative, or elſe both as they had long stood, ſo in a trace were to fall together, and the glorious Church and Monarchy of England to run the ſame baſe fates with Democraticall Scotland. This unexpected hurli-burly (as there was iuſt cauſe) ſoone put your Maiesties ſacred Clergy out of theſe devout offices, which held the peoples hearts unto them, and we became a ſort of men cheap and contemptible, untill at length it pleaſed God by a new aſſeſſion of Martiall vigour to ſtrengthen your Maieſties ſacred arme, and to rouſe up the ſleepie courage of your liege people ſo farre that the greater and better part of your Kingdome were animated to declare to fight for your maieſties rights (a large portion of which have no other fountaine then your Clergies height, and nearneſſe to your Maieſtie) ſince which time (your Mateſtie and we all can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but with exultation acknowledge) by the Cathedrall prayers of your Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy as well as by the ſwords <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> theſe ſonn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of Mars, the heroick Cavaliert ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny glorious victories haue been obtained as at Keinton, Branford, Marlebo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, Cirencester &amp; in the North, all which and the reſt, which are yet to come are under God, wholly to be attributed to the ſpeciall reſpect the Allmighty beares to your Moſt Religious Perſon, and to the Canonicall, Cathedrall Prayers of your upper Clergy ſo that now your Maieſties, &amp; your Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es glorie, ſeemes only to have been Eclipſed for a time that it might ſhine forth again in fuller ſtrength &amp; gaine new beams by that diſconſolate interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Yet after all theſe teſtimoates from heaven of the truth of your Maieſties cauſe, one particular there is, by the demerits whereof without early prevention we may chance to hazzard all our happineſſe in the very haven, and that is it,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111121:5"/>which with ſubmiſſion to your Majeſties divine judgement I ſhall now take the boldneſſe in a few words to diſcover, and it is none other then that moſt unhappy ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident caſt in of late, no doubt by the impure hand of Satan, nay to blaſt our bud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, nay almoſt flouriſhing hopes, that unparalelled profanation of Gods and your Majeſties Churches, which I began to looke at, at the entrance of this my addreſſe to your Majeſty, but was diverted and thruſt aſide by thoſe uncivill juſtlers of Monarchy it ſelfe, whom I could not but for a time let flie at, even in the preſence of your Majeſty; returning therefore from whence I have ſo long digreſſed, I ſhall now by your Majeſties pardon and patience, cloze this humble tender of my duty and conſcience in a briefe repreſentation of this horrid fact, and the inconveniences, or miſchiefes rather; which either have already, or will in reaſon infallibly attend it. The fact ſuch, that I feare thoſe ſo effectuall <hi>Cathedrall</hi> oriſons of your Clergy, without ſome ſpeciall miracle of mercy from heaven upon them, cannot expiate, and therefore the miſchiefes which muſt attend, will correſpond to the deſerts of ſuch a Cauſe, if a timely humiliation ward them not off from us; I cannot then (dread So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne) longer diſſemble that, which is the joy and hope of your enemies, and a raſor upon the hearts of your moſt faithfull Subjects, That too well, and too far violation of two of our neighbour Churches here in <hi>Oxford,</hi> that of Saint <hi>Giles,</hi> and <hi>Maudlins</hi> Pariſh, into which your <hi>Provoſt Marſhall</hi> (no doubt for want of other convenience, but that ſatisfies not) thruſt that Rebellious crew which a late Victory brought from <hi>Cirenceſter:</hi> I have heard the like was done at <hi>Kingſton,</hi> but I will not beleeve it, oh that no man knew or beleeved this, it is the beſt wiſh I can breathe out, next unto that, it had not at all been done, but done it is, I would there were an Act of oblivion paſt upon it, at leaſt I would we could as eaſily ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther up the infamy of it, as it might have been prevented: Your Majeſty I know is cleare and innocent from this great offence, may the puniſhment fall upon that head which firſt conceived it, and may your ſacred Majeſty be untoucht, better your Church, your Kingdome fall, then your ſacred perſon feele but one twinge of the toothache: How loath me thinkes I am to ſpeake out all, how officiouſly my fancy ſtirs my tongue to other matters, but my thoughts will not, out it muſt, leſt it burſt in the delivery, your Churches (gracious Soveraigne) your Churches are diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured defiled, become an abomination in the ſight of heaven, your Churches only dedicated to heavenly uſes, are made to ſerve the vileſt offices. Neither the ſacred Font, that fountaine of ſpirituall life, nor the bleſſed Altar, that heaven upon earth, where Chriſt vouchſafed us more then his ſpirituall preſence, can ſay I am not pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted, I am not vile and contemptible, can the enemy ſay leſſe, where is now their God? Certainly he will ſay, what is become of that reverence, that proſtration, that opinion of holineſſe, uſed and ſaid to be in Churches, was all that ſervice but a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:111121:6"/>frolicke, but a toy, but a ſcene made to ſerve the times, and Churchmens turnes, will the next courſe of ſerving God be thought other then another frolicke, a hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, a baſe accommodation to the times? Will your Reverend Fathers be hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter beleeved, When they ſhall gravely tell that too much reverence cannot be uſed in the houſe of God, where God hath a ſpeciall reſidence, is more preſent then elſewhere in the world who can with ſilence, with patience, ſee God himſelfe put out of his poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, and nor be Martyrs in the vindication of ſuch Sacriledge? Were there not houſes to be found in your Majeſties territories capable of theſe miſcreants, beſides your Churches? Let me once ſpeake with freedome to your Majeſty, better had it been that theſe Rebels had yet remained unquelled, that theſe enemies of your Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter had yet exalted themſelves, then that your God ſhould have been thus diſhonour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, better had it been to have fled before our enemies, then that our God ſhould have been put to flight, and chaſed from amongst us, and that in time of need, when Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, nay more, Epiſcopacy is ſo boldly aſſaulted. I feare dread Soveraigne, I would this feare were groundleſſe, that <hi>Wallers</hi> late Victories, and the conſternati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of your Subjects, owe themſelves to no other cauſe, then the profanation of theſe Churches, thoſe enemies of your Crown and heaven, though no friends to Churches, were yet ſo modeſt, or ſo politicke, as not to adventure upon this way of incenſing heaven, untill they ſaw Gods juſtice ingaged againſt your party in ſome notable ſtroke of vengeance, ſo religious they were, as not to be leaders in the crime: I have done, and my hearts deſire it is, that future misfortunes makes not your Majeſty too ſenſible of the truth of that which is the ſilence of others who better might have ſpoken, Command of conſcience only bad me ſay,</p>
                     <closer>Vivat Rex Carolus.</closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>Such a Homily as this would, whether you reſpect the flattery, the blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, the ſuperſtition, or the ſpightfull excurſions not amiſſe have ſuited with the grave managing of a <hi>Cathedrall</hi> beard, and I wonder that none of all that rout of <hi>Cathedrall</hi> fugitives which now embaſe the Court, had not remembred to beſtow on his Majeſty one caſt of their wonted zeale in this argument, but the truth is, the bouncing of Guns, the prauncing of Horſes, the ratling of Armes, the pledging of healths, and the curſing of Schiſmaticks and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments have disfurniſhed our <hi>Cathedrall</hi> Droanes of all thoughts of the holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Churches; alas, when Epiſcopacy it ſelfe is ſo fiercely ſtruck at, nay wounded in a vitall part, can a Biſhop have the leaſure, in ſuch a time when all thoughts and induſtry is too little in ſeeking plaiſters for the wounds of Epiſcopacy, to trouble and diſtract his minde about the ſervice of God, and holineſſe of Churches; indeed a time of deep peace was ſeaſonable for ſuch thoughts, a time hewne out for the advancement of Churches and Churchmens
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:111121:6"/>pomp, was now indiſcreetly allowed to the ungratiating of Churches both with King and People: but the depth of <hi>Cathedrall</hi> miſeries now it is, that it can only be ſaid, ſuch times lately were, when the wheele of Fortune is turned, and the robuſtious ſouldier ſits uppermoſt, and at the next whirle the inexo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Seperatiſt may chance to perk up, <hi>Cathedrall</hi> men may commendably leave off tithing Mint and Cummin, leave off talking of Altars, and holineſſe of Churches, and ſadly meditate on thoſe weightier matters, of maintaining wives and children, of ſecuring their Carkaſes from the Parliament, and their houſes from that terrible word <hi>Plunder:</hi> Me thinkes I heare a <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrall</hi> Humble Bee buzzing out ſome ſuch dolefull ſtraines as theſe, Oh that there had been ſo much providence in our Velvet Nodles, as to have thought there might have been a Parliament, and ſuch ſhrewd heads in it, that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards and Grace of a King cannot purchaſe ſuch as can overmatch them, which yet ſeemes very ſtrange, eſpecially ſince ſuch care was taken to bring idleneſſe and licentiouſneſſe in faſhion both at the Innes of Court, and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities, ſo that it had been (one would thinke) an eaſie matter for a Prince, in whoſe hand was the ſtaple of all preferments, to have had choiſe of inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for any ſervice, eſpecially by the concurrent aſſiſtance of the Law and the Goſpell, but yet which way ſoever it came about, improvident we were, and irreſpective of afterclaps, elſe we might have laid up friends in <hi>Banke,</hi> even amongſt the Seperatiſts themſelves, which now would have beſteed us in time of need, ſomwhat in prudence might have been abated in the rigorous exaction of Ceremonies, the Canons in force might have been executed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpightfulneſſe and delight, in the puniſhment of ſuch as were found tardy, Churches might have been adorned like Matrons, not tricked up like ſtrum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, like the Idolatrous Temples of Rome, enough might have been done to draw on devotion, though all had been omitted which ſerved to erect a wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton love to Churches, it might have been ſaid, and ſcarſe gainſaid, that Churches were fitly both raiſed and uſed for the publike ſervice of God, it needed not to have been added an unexpreſſable holineſſe was impreſſed on the walls, by meanes of conſecration, and then if an urgent neceſſity, as ſince hath happened (but then I beleeve had never been) had turned a Church into a Priſon, it might fairely have been ſaid, that Church had loſt its uſe, not loſt that holineſſe it never had, and then this vile practiſe of the Cavaleers had not thus ſtuck like a bur of infamy in our Cathedrall throates, ſhall I ſay, or upon our conſciences, if any ſuch thing we have hardlier, to be removed then taking up Armes againſt our Prince, from the tender Conſcience of an honeſt Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt, neither then (ſay I) had there been occaſion to have raiſed or reſolved
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:111121:7"/>theſe two queſtions mentioned in the frontiſpeece, which in the laſt place call for a diſpatch, and the firſt was this:
<q>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Whether the Seperatiſt (as he is called) who makes his houſe, or (as it is ſaid) his Barne a Church, be more ſcandalous, or the Cavalier (who look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing another way in his diſcourſe and profeſſion) hath at <hi>Oxford,</hi> where his Majeſtie reſides, turned Churches (with reverence be it ſpoken) into priſons, and Jakes, and in <hi>Devon:</hi> at many places into Stables.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This Queſtion ſeemes to be, and is, I beleeve, in ſome mens apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, a Caſe of Conſcience, yet, I feare me, little will be contributed either from the Popiſh, or Proteſtant Caſuiſts towards the deciſion: for, as I gueſſe, they have not heard of it, much leſſe handled it; nevertheleſſe feare not, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Reader, but that it may be fairely determined, for I have heard a wiſe man ſay, that a tollerable underſtanding beſt ſtates a point of Conſcience, when there is leaſt of theſe Caſuiſts both directions and judgements in it. Give me leave firſt to explaine ſome things in the Queſtion, and then thou ſhalt have my iudgement, ſuch as it is, in this weighty matter. Firſt then, by the Sepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt I meane all thoſe people of new or old <hi>England,</hi> who either will not, or elſe have no great heart to ioyne in the outward worſhip of God, with any, be their learning or eſteem what it will, who make a conſcience of the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call policy, or Diſcipline of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as it was lately mannaged by the Archbiſhops, Biſhops, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, I adde that Parentheſis <hi>(as they are called)</hi> to imply that in my judgement, though they are uſually ſo called by the adverſe party, yet they are ill called Seperatiſts, for (good men) they agree throughout with the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall Proteſtant, in the maine of Gods worſhip, and in the whole Doctrine of the Goſpell, but Seperatiſt only in that, wherein they are in conſcience per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded they ought not, and the adverſe party cannot, in the judgement of any indifferent man convince them, that they ought to joyne unto them: Indeed when it ſhall be made cleare, or certaine, that they ought to joyne with the <hi>Cathedrall</hi> party, and then they ſhall ſtand off, I alſo ſhall be well conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to have them Chriſtened Seperatiſts.</p>
            <p>In the meane time I wonder that any, at leaſt iudicious men, ſhould faſten a terme of diſgrace (for ſo it is accounted) upon men both upright in their lives, and Orthodox in their tenets, meerly for not according with them in a humour, for not complying in a point of outward uniformity, when variety (for ought hath beene ſaid to the contrary) hath both as much decency, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:111121:7"/>might have for its companion, as much charity, in my poore iudgement (which I profeſſe in Gods ſight is impreiudiced for ought I know in this cauſe) men may as well call him a Seperatiſt, that betakes himſelfe from one neighbourhood to another, or from one Corporation to another; for as ſuch a man may be as good a Subiect to his King in both places, though hee obſerve not the ſame Cuſtomes, and ſhould be accounted ſo; in like manner the other whom heedleſſe men call a Seperatiſt, keeping the Relation to God, and his people inviolable, ſo farre as God Commands him, at leaſt ſincerely indeavouring it, is capable of, and ſhould have our Charitie, and good opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion (though he differed from us in theſe outward Ceremonies) as cordially, as he that moſt of all complies with us, nay, more many times, if reaſon may be heard, for many agree with the <hi>Cathedrall men</hi> meerely out of faſhion, and this man differs out of conſcience, and what man, who is ſound in the Head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peece, likes not a man better than a <hi>Jacke-an-Apes,</hi> at leaſt each wiſeman ſhould doe ſo.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, when, I ſay, [<hi>That the Seperatiſt makes his houſe</hi> or (as its ſaid) <hi>his Barne a Church</hi>] I ſpeake it againe in the words of his Calumniators, for it hath not yet beene made apparent that he doth either, at leaſt, not the latter, how ever it is not their conſtant opinion (who beare that name) that Churches ſhould be diſus'd, and Barnes, or private Houſes ſerve in ſtead of Churches, onely this much is true, that in regard they are offended at the Cuſtomes and humane impoſitions in our publike worſhip, they chuſe rather to ſerve God in their private houſes, or it may be any where, then omit the performance of ſo neceſſary a duty, ſo that what they now doe is onely <hi>In caſu neceſſitatis,</hi> and whilſt our publike places of worſhip are not open, at leaſt, for the foppiſh Ceremonies uſed in them are offenſive to them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Fourthly, the burthen of the <hi>Quere</hi> reſting upon theſe words <hi>[More ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous]</hi> It is but convenient that this phraſe of compariſon be well weighed: Firſt then, I would not have any man hence inferre, that the practiſe of the Seperatiſt is at all ſcandalous in propriety of ſpeech, becauſe I am about to prove the practiſe of the Cavaliers is more ſcandalous, for the ſcandall which ariſeth from the practiſe of the <hi>Nonconformiſt</hi> (for ſo may he moſt fitly be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, unleſſe you pleaſe to call him, what in very truth he is, an honeſt man,) is only <hi>Scandalum acceptum,</hi> a poſitive Scandall, a ſcandall in fancie and opinion only, wheras that of the Cavalier is <hi>Scandalum datum</hi> an active ſcandall, a ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall in truth and reallity: Secondly, I would thus be conceiv'd that to any man that makes a conſcience of his ways, the Practiſe of the Cavaliers upon ſuppt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fition of their owne principles touching the holineſſe of Churches, which
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:111121:8"/>the Seperatiſt conceives, and that truely moſt falſe, is, at leaſt ought to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted more offenſive, even to the men of their own party, as having in it a juſt cauſe of ſcandall, then the practiſe of the Non-conformiſts; ſuppoſe all true which is obiected, can be either to the Cavalier, or any Chriſtian whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, the former being truely ſcandalous, the latter in a groundleſſe opinion onely, and therefore the former is more ſcandalous; nevertheleſſe leaving the indifferent Reader to his owne judgement touching what is ſcandalous, or more ſcandalous, I ſhall, I doubt not, by the Reaſons following make it evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <hi>ad hominem,</hi> at leaſt that the practiſe of the Cavalier is moſt ſcancaious, and that out of the notorious Poſition of their owne party.</p>
            <p>Firſt, then one point of their Divinity is, that Irreverence in Churches is ſcandalous upon this ground; they condemne all ſuch as bow not at the Name of <hi>Jeſus;</hi> all ſuch as receive not the bleſſed Sacrament Kneeling, all ſuch as bow not at the Altar, or ſtand not up at <hi>Gloria Patri, &amp;c.</hi> as ſcandalous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, whence I ſubſume, that if theſe men are upon theſe titles ſcandalous, then <hi>a fortiori,</hi> much more the Cavaliers, who by diſhonouring, by polluting, and unhallowing whole Churches, at once caſheeres all thoſe obſervances, the very neglect whereof in others they cry up as ſcandalous.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, another principle of theirs is, That throwing downe of Organs, ſilencing of Cathedrall Roarers and Squeakers, overturning of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolls, battering of Paint and Images, pulling up railes, aſſaulting of Surpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Common-Prayer-Bookes is ſcandalous, whence I likewiſe inferre <hi>a fortiori,</hi> that thus violating of whole Churches, and prophaning and unhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing all the ſacred Utenſils of Churches is much more ſcandalous, which is the knowne gracious practiſes of the holy Cavaliers.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A third Poſition of theirs is, that by vertue of Conſecration there is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed an holineſſe on Churches, and therefore ſuch as unhallow them in any kinde are eminently ſcandalous, yet the Cavalier (whoſe Doctrine this is) notwithſtanding this holineſſe of Churches, converts Churches into Stables, Priſons, Jakes, a worſer unhallowneſſe then which cannot be immagined, unleſſe the Cavaliers themſelves quartered in Churches, and by their blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Oathes, Execrations, ribaldry, made their Church (which their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience would not ſtartle at) their hell.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Fourthly, and laſtly, they Vote unanimouſly that the Seperatiſt, who makes his Houſe or Barne a Church is truely ſcandalous, and if ſo, then let any man of conſcience or judgement, tell me whether the Cavalier be not much more ſcandaſous, who in ſtead of making his Houſe and Barne a Church, transformes his Church to what was ſaid before. That this laſt Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:111121:8"/>may have (as its fit) its full weight and emphaſis, conſider with me (good Reader) for a ſhort time;
<list>
                  <item>Firſt, the Fact of the Seperatiſt with the aggravations of it.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, the Fact of the Cavaliers and its aggravation.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And then by an equall ballancing or comparing them together, any man may eaſtly diſcerne whether of the twaine is more impious and ſcandalous, the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratiſt or the Cavalier.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, the Separatiſts Fact is, that he makes his Houſe or Barne a Church, for let that alſo for once be admitted, which yet hath not beene pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, but by Fame, which is uſually a Lyer, now what it is to make an Houſe or Barne a Church? and wherein lies the hainouſneſſe and offence of him that doth ſo? I anſwer, to make a private Houſe or Barne a Church, is either to doe the Offices which are proper to a Church, or to allow the Offices which are proper to a Church to be done in a private Houſe or Barne; what theſe Offices are, thoſe of the Cavaliers who come to Church cannot be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of, and they are chiefely; 1. Preaching or Expounding the Scriptures. 2. Adminiſtring the Sacraments; unto which you may adde, if you pleaſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſecondary things; 1. Prayer. Secondly, Marriage. Thirdly, Burying, and then either all, or moſt, or ſome at leaſt of theſe muſt be done by the Sepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, or any other that makes his Houſe or Barne a Church.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, the aggravation or crime of the Seperatiſts fact is this. 1. That he <hi>[the Seperatiſt]</hi> who poſſibly, or probably, or certainly is not in holy orders, that is, hath not been ſanctified by any Biſhops ſacred Clutch, now appointed ſolemnly to the performance of ſuch holy duties, yet uſurpes and dares to doe the office of him, that hath been thus conſecrated or hallowed unto them. 2. That he the Seperatiſt, a laymean, and not of the Clergy, dares doe theſe offices in a private houſe, or which is more, in a barne, in the audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Rats and Mice, which ſhould only be done. 1. By Clergy men. 2. In conſecrated hollowed places. 3. His fact is aggravated by the Law which hee violates in ſo doing, which is firſt the Statute Law of the Laud, as they ſay, Secondly, The Laws and conſtitutions of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Thirdly, the Canon Law, or the Popes Law (which <hi>Luther</hi> called <hi>merdam Papalem</hi>) and which yet ſticks upon, and layes hold on us, where it is not againſt the Lawes of God, or of the Land; as they ſay, Fourthly, his fact is further ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravated, 1. By the time, for he is generally ſaid to doe theſe offices at an uncanonicall time, as in the night, or when he liſts, when the Spirit (as the Cavaliere Phraſes it ſweetly) moves him. 2. By the manner of doing it, which is, they ſay, 1. In ſpight and oppoſition to the Hierarchie. 2. Without theſe holy weeds, and cuſtomes of Veſtments, as Surplice, Cap, Cope, Croſier,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:111121:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:111121:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:111121:10"/>Rochet, Gowne, Canonicall Coat, conſecrated ſlippers, without cringings, proſtrations, ſtations, or converſions to the Eaſt. 5. All this he doth out of conſcience, and full perſwaſion that what he doth is more acceptable to God. And are not theſe, my friend, haynous things, and unſufferable in a Church, and Chriſtian commonwealth, and offenſive to all that heare of, and ſee it?</p>
            <p>In the next place conſider with me the fact of the Cavaleer, with its aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations.</p>
            <p>His fact is, that he converts the Churches of God into Barnes, Stables, Jakes, that is, he either doth himſelfe, or cauſeth to be done (which is not an haires bredth to chuſe) the ſame offices in Churches which are proper to Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Stables, Jakes. And now heare the aggravation of his fact: He <hi>[The Cavalier]</hi> who maintain that Churches are not to be defiled, who holds that there is an holineſſe in Churches, who condemnes, and would gladly deſtroy the Seperatiſt for his rudeneſſe even toward Church-implements, he the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor part, nay the totall of whoſe devotion and religion it is to have God alone ſerved in Churches, and with thoſe Ceremonies which the Seperatiſt abhors, in ſhort, he who had rather be a Papiſt, then part with ſuch ceremonies. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, yet he <hi>[The Cavaleer]</hi> not only unhallows the Utenſils of Churches, but profanes the Churches themſelves, and for the manner and meaſure as bad, if not worſe then the <hi>Goth,</hi> or <hi>Turke,</hi> for can a <hi>Turke</hi> or <hi>Goth</hi> doe more vilely then make a ſtable or jakes of a Church? Thirdly, his fact is aggravated by the time, and what is the time when the Cavaleer doth thus diſhonour Churches? even when he fights to maintaine the honour of Churches, when he kils the Seperatiſt for tampering with ſomething in Churches. Fourthly, He doth all this where his Maieſty reſides, in an Univerſity, in the ſight of the Reverend clergy, who have ſo conſtantly preached and written in the defence of the holineſſe of Churches. Nay, fifthly, he is not only content to doe, and approve, and applaud this vile fact himſelfe, but hath likewiſe corrupted the judgements of the grave Fathers of our Church, hath drawne them into the ſociety of this crime, he hath got the lights of our Church to legitimate his black impiety. Sixthly, by his fact he hath violated all the Laws, and Canons in this bahalfe like an arrant Seperatiſt. And laſtly, all this he hath done, even whileſt he is throughly reſolved, and perſwaded in conſcience, that he ought to have done the contrary, nay when he knew that all his party are ſcandali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed at the rudeneſſe of the Seperatiſt, which yet is not to be named the ſame day with this prodious <hi>Gothique.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now (my friend) what thinkeſt thou, how many bowes ſhort is the Cavaleer off the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt?</p>
            <p>In the laſt place, let us ponder and ballance (as I promiſed to doe) theſe facts thus qualified as you have heard.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:111121:10"/>
            <p>Firſt, then the Seperatiſt offends out of ſillineſſe and ignorance, and at leaſt pretendeth conſcience for what he doth, but the Cavalier in regard of his wiſdome and knowledge doth all this even againſt conſcience. Secondly, the Seperatiſt by his rudeneſſe offends onely the Cavalier his mortall enemy, but the Cavalier his owne party, his friends of whom he ſhould be moſt ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Thirdly, The Sepreatiſt is offenſive onely for not joyning with the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier in ſome outward, and as the Seperatiſt is perſwaded an indifferent part of Gods Worſhip, but the Cavaliers in that which he judgeth moſt neceſſary.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Seperatiſt is offenſive for running in Common with the Cavalier, but the Cavalier takes in horſes, and lets them runne in Common with the Groomes in Gods Houſe, as at <hi>Kingſton, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. The Saperatiſt cannot be perſwaded that he violates any Law of God or man, but the Cavalier knowes that he violates all Lawes.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, the Seperatiſt is frequent in the ſervice of God at home, and at Church he will heare Sermons, but the Cavalier ſerves the devill at home, and his revenge and his horſes at Church; and now let my Cavalier, who is not drunke or mad (if any ſuch may be found) judge whether is more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane and ſcandalous, He, or the Seperatiſt.</p>
            <p>How gladly would I learne what the moſt profound Cathedrall Doctor in <hi>Oxford</hi> could Anſwer to theſe Reaſons, what evaſions they could excogitate, for reconciling the practiſe of their Patrons with their acknowledged Doctrine.</p>
            <p>But alas! what reaſon hath any man at this time, of all times, to expect ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilties from <hi>Oxford,</hi> where before the King came thither, when Sacke aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in their Tavernes, the height of judgement was but ſome frothy <hi>Nonſcence</hi> raptures of wit, but ſince (God knowes) by reaſon of that long unhappy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorce betweene their braines and the ſpirit of Sacke, nothing hath flow'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the ſad complexion of dull Ale, and Colledge Taplaſh.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſſe though I utterly deſpaire of ſatisfaction from them, I will be ſo courteous as to lend them a word of Counſell, and to wiſh them capable of it, and it is this: That ſince the world is ſo offended with this beaſtly fact of their Minions, and diſappointed of all juſt and reaſonable Apologies for it, from themſelves, they would exhort very earneſtly the Cavaliers, and others whom it may concerne, to play an after-game of Repentance and Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo that at leaſt they might skin over that wound which they cannot heale.</p>
            <p>The Church Story not impertinently to this purpoſe, makes mention of a <hi>Mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſſian</hi> Prince (as I remember) called <hi>Cabares,</hi> who purſuing the <hi>Gothes</hi> and <hi>Vandalls</hi> with an huge Army, ſtill in his paſſage as he went, cleanſed all
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:111121:11"/>thoſe Churches, which that impure Nation had deſir'd; and would it not be an exemplary peece of piety, and much tending to the honour of your party with poſterity? Firſt, if the Cavaliers would in their hands, or mouthes, or any other more fitting way carry out the filth of thoſe Churches, which by a more than <hi>Gothiſh</hi> impiety they have deſiled; and then ſecondly, if the Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Cleargy would humble themſelves ſo low as to come after the Cavaliers, and with their Cathedrall Beeſome-like Beards ſweepe them; and ſo much be ſpoken touching our firſt Queſtion: the ſecond was,
<q>Whether Churches thus prophaned, and fallen from Grace and holineſſe are not by the Biſhops to be conſecrated.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Of which Queſtion with all manner of expedition: Firſt then the Puritans here, ſo much he is for holineſſe, would, I warrant you, goe neare to hold they ought, if he thought,
<list>
                  <item>1. Firſt, That there were no neede of conſecrating Churches.</item>
                  <item>2. Secondly, that any holineſſe were ſtampt on Churches by the Miniſtry of Conſecration.</item>
                  <item>3. And thirdly, that Churches could fall from Grace or holineſſe, once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, but holding neither of theſe, its probable that his iudgement ſtands for the negative.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, on the other ſide the <hi>Cathedrall</hi> Doctors maintaining with one conſent; 1. A neceſſity of Conſecrating Churches. 2. Undiſcernable Characters of holineſſe impreſſed on Churches. 3. Falling from Grace in the beſt Saints of God, much more inanimate Churches muſt in reaſon be thought to hold the affirmative, and that Churches thus deſiled ought to be reconſecrated, eſpecially conſidering,</p>
            <p>Firſt, That Conſecration of Churches is an holy and heavenly Work, which begets an high and reverend eſteeme in the people; for ſay the people, the Biſhops muſt needs be eminently holy men, who can make dead Churches holy, and therefore at this time when Biſhops have beene much vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified, all occaſions ſhould be catcht at, for a reingendring in the people a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verentiall conceit of theſe holy Fathers; and therefore reconſecration not to be paſt by.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Conſidering that it may chance to be ſcandalous, and to their brethren of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> not to have theſe unhallowed Churches (though in pollicie made ſo at their inſtigation) reconſecrated, of whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences they ought to be very tender, in requitall of their bowells of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion towards the Biſhops cauſe lately in much ieopardy to have beene
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:111121:11"/>conſumed by the fiery zeale of the Schiſmaticks, had not that holy man of <hi>Rome</hi> and his agents beſtirred their ſtumps, and brought more than holy wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for the extinguiſhing of that flame.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, conſidering that the Conſecration of a Church, which is no great labour, and brings no benefit at all, either to Auditors or ſpectators (which is at length to be thought on, leaſt the People by the Biſhops meanes grow too Holy, and too knowing, as of late it ſell out, both to their ſhame and ſmart) will ſave the good Father a Sermon for that weeke of Conſecrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is well ſaved, eſpecially ſince experience hath atught the Church of late, that Sermons have done ſo much miſcheeſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Fourthly, conſidering that at the reconſecrating of every Church, there ought to be a conſecration Dinner at the charge of the Pariſh, which will be comfortable both to his Lordſhips old corps and no falſe Latin in his purſe by ſaving a meale after theſe hard pinching times, which had almoſt exhauſted all, and <hi>tantum non,</hi> brought <hi>rem ad repem,</hi> that is, brought his good Lordſhip within a cloſe or two off the Beggar.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, conſidering that ſo few Churches are in theſe peeviſh times erected, and therfore though there be no great need (ſuppoſing Churches cleanſed and ſwept as was above adviſed) of reconſecration of them, yet leaſt the holy Father ſhould forget the trick of it, and ſo the Country People, in caſe there be at any time an occaſion of conſecration, and the boyes ſhoud have matter miniſtred unto them to laugh at his Lordſhip, when poſſible he ſhould be (through diſuſe) to ſeeke what to doe next.</p>
            <p>Yet notwithſtanding all theſe ſtrong reaſons for the reconſecration of Churches, it ſeemes not onely expedient but neceſſary not to reconſecrate them. 1. In caſe the Kings Maieſtie or the Queen, or the Privy Councell, or the Chiefe Prelate then in higheſt place, do not approve it. 2. In caſe there can be no conſecration dinner, or a poore one. 3. In caſe the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> declare to the contrary, and Laſtly, in caſe his Lordſhip be decrepit, and cannot trample about all the time without danger of having a fit of the gout, or ſtone, and then it ſhall be thought ſufficent that his Lordſhip either omit the duty, or conſe crate onely the new Boards, Poaſts or other Utenſills, which were not before conſecrated, that ſo a greater good may be conſulted. <hi>viz:</hi> his good Lordſhips eaſe, and indeed were I freely to give my Judgment, this much (if any thing at all were to be done) would be enough, for my private opinion it is (gentle Reader pardon me that I tell not from whence I had it, untill I know my Authors pleaſure from whom I had it, whether I may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veale it) that conſecration is a kinde of Baptiſme, and therefore ſhould not
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:111121:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:111121:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:111121:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:111121:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:111121:14"/>be iterated, leaſt wee ſimbolize too farr with the curſed Anabaptiſt, and therefore onely the new parts of a Church ſhould be conſcerated, no part reconſecrated, and yet in this new way there are new difficulties, not a few, as if Conſecration be a kind of Baptiſme, why ſhould not a man, who hath beene Baptized in his infancy, be rebaptized when he is growne a great Lubber, and hath gotten much new fleſh about him, as well as a Church re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive conſecration in the new parts of it; and many more ſuch difficulties I could with more eaſe conjure up then put them downe againe, but I beleeve ſuch are niceties, which a man may be ignorant of, or elſe Holy Church will hereafter reſolve them, if we can have the patience to waite her leaſure, and ſo I ſhake hands with this perplexed Caſe touching the reconſecration of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hallowed Churches.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
